Finding Aid for Flint Woolen Mills Records, 1851-1910
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Flint Woolen Mills Records 1851-1910
Flint Woolen Mills
851219 Bb.2/2; BB.2 Outsize
Records of the business enterprises of Oren Stone of Stony Run (later South Grand Blanc) and Flint, Michigan. The firms were known variously as Flint Woolen Mill, Stone Woolen Mill and Stone, Atwood and Co. Also includes daybooks and ledgers detailing the operation of his general stores in Stony Run and Flint, Michigan, and letter books, invoices, journals, cashbooks, order books, ledgers, and other business records from the woolen mill business.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
19 linear feet 232 volumes and 1 folder
1 oversize volumes
The record group was the gift of Dwight Stone (donor no. 1147 ) and came to the library in 1940.
The record group is open to research.
Oren Stone was founder and owner of the Flint Woolen Mills of Flint, Michigan. Born in Auburn, New York in 1833, Stone moved with his family to Stony Run (later south Grand Blanc) in Genesee County in 1844. While here, he operated his first mercantile venture, a general store. Moving to Flint in 1857, he established another general store operation. In 1867, he founded the Flint Woolen Mills. Although owned by Stone, this establishment was operated by Stone, Atwood & Co., whose members included, in addition to Stone, W. A. Atwood, J. N. Blake, and E. W. Atwood. The mills under Stone's direction was known primarily as a manufacturer of cashmeres and blankets. In partnership with David Traxler, Stone broadened the scope of his interests with the establishment of the Flint Pantaloon Co. in 1896. Stone was also a large owner of Flint real estate, including Stone's Opera House. He held many local offices, serving as mayor of Flint in 1888.
The records of the business enterprises of Oren Stone consist of 232 volumes and a folder of miscellaneous loose items. Beginning in 1851 when Stone was working in Stony Run, the records extend up to 1910. The collection includes some of the records of Stone's mercantile activities in Stony Run and Flint primarily in the 1850's and 1860's. The great bulk of the collection, however, pertains directly to the activities of the Flint Woolen Mills. Since 1867, these have been arranged by type of record, including letterpress books of correspondence, invoices, order books, cashbooks, inventories, ledgers, journals, and daybooks. Some of the records relate to specific activities within the mill such as knitting, carding, spinning, weaving and finishing, and dyeing.
Subjects:
Business records.; Flint (Mich.); General stores--Michigan--Flint.; General stores--Michigan--Stony Run.; Genesee County (Mich.); Stone, Oren, b. 1833.; Stone, Atwood & Company (Flint, Mich.); Stone Woolen Mills (Flint, Mich.); Stony Run (Mich.); Wool industry--Michigan--Flint.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.
- Oren Stone Mercantile Interests
  - Order book 1851-1853 [Stony Run, Oakland County] (Box 1)
  - Bills payable and receivable 1856-1863 (Box 1)
  - Bills payable and receivable 1859-1867 (Box 1)
  - Daybooks
    - November 1854-August 1855 [Stone and Hadley-Stony Run] (Box 1)
    - November 1856-November 1859 (Box 1)
    - June 1859-March 1860 (Box 1)
    - February 1861-July 1862 (Box 1)
    - March-August 1862 (Box 1)
    - August 1862-November 1862 (Box 1)
    - November 1862-February 1863 (Box 1)
    - June 1863-January 1865 [Stone and Burr] (Box 2)
    - October 1866-March 1867 (Box 2)
  - Cashbooks
    - October 1856-1858 [Stony Run] (Box 2)
      (with cashbook, 1873-1874)
    - June 1863-July, 1864 [Stone and Burr] (Box 2)
    - July 1865-October 1866 (Box 2)
  - Ledgers
    - September 1858-July 1860 (Box 2)
    - 1860-July 1863 (Box 2)
    - June 1863-February 1870 (Box 2)
    - March 1864-March 1867 [Owosso Store] (Box 2)
  - Account book October 1856-August 1858 (Box 3)
  - Stock book 1860-1863 (Box 3)
  - Purchase book September 1853-circa June 1855 (Box 3)
  - Journal January 1874-September 1875 (Box 3)
  - Journal February 1875-January 1877 (Box 3)
    (Stone French & Co. in account with Stone and Stewart)
  - Journal June 1897-November 1900 (Box 3)
    (estate of Ann Stone)
- Flint Woolen Mills
  - Letterpress books
    - February 1887-August 1888 (Box 4)
    - May 1889-July 1890 (Box 4)
    - July 1890-April 1891 (Box 4)
    - April 1891-September 1891 (Box 4)
    - September 1891-December 1891 (Box 4)
    - December 1891-April 1892 (Box 4)
    - April-August 1892 (Box 4)
    - April 1893-October 1893 (Box 5)
    - October 1893-February 1894 (Box 5)
    - February-May 1894 (Box 5)
    - May-September 1894 (Box 5)
    - September 1894-January 1895 (Box 5)
    - January-April 1895 (Box 5)
    - April-July 1895 (Box 5)
    - July-October 1895 (Box 6)
    - October 1895-January 1896 (Box 6)
    - January-April 1896 (Box 6)
    - August-December 1896 (Box 6)
    - December 1899-May 1900 (Box 6)
    - March-July 1900 (Box 6)
    - May-September 1906 (Box 6)
    - February-September 1908 (Box 7)
    - April-December 1909 (Box 7)
    - December 1892-April 1895 [cashmere dept.] (Box 7)
    - March 1894-October 1901 (Box 7)
    - May-June (Box 7)
      (no year)
  - Invoice books
    - February 1887-September 1888 (Box 7)
    - September 1888-September 1889 (Box 7)
    - May 1893-August 1894 (Box 7)
    - August 1894-July 1895 (Box 8)
    - July 1895-March 1896 (Box 8)
    - January-December 1900 (Box 8)
    - August-December 1904 (Box 8)
    - January 1906-June 1908 (Box 8)
    - June 1908-October 1908 (Box 8)
    - October 1910-July 1910 (Box 8)
  - Spinning Room Books, 19 volumes (Box 9)
    - 1880-1881 (Box 9)
    - 1886-1888 (Box 9)
    - 1891-1894 (Box 9)
    - 1896-1905 (Box 9)
    - 1908-1910 (Box 9)
  - Cloth Book-Made and sold 1906-1908 (Box 10)
  - Sales and Commission Book 1902-1905 (Box 10)
  - Sample books, 4 volumes (Box 10)
  - Cloth book 1867-1870 (Box 10)
  - American Express Co. receipt book (Box 10)
  - Outside lines book 1907-1908 (Box 10)
  - Custom work book 1898-1903 (Box 10)
  - Pettycash book (Box 10)
  - Dyehouse book February 1887-March 1889 (Box 10)
  - Dyehouse book September 1889-April 1893 (Box 10)
  - Want book (Box 10)
  - Scrapbook concerning insurance cases undated (Box 10)
  - Trial balance book 1893 (Box 11)
  - Trial balance book 1904 (Box 11)
  - Knitting account book 1881-1886 (Box 11)
  - Spooling room book 1872-1886 (Box 11)
  - Carding room books 1869-1877, 1880-1884, 1888-1892, 5 volumes (Box 11)
  - Lot books, 4 volumes
    - 1880 (Box 11)
    - 1893-1898 (Box 11)
    - 1898-1901 (Box 11)
    - 1901-1905 (Box 11)
  - Time books, 6 volumes
    - 1867-1871 (Box 11)
    - 1882-1883 (Box 11)
    - 1889 (Box 11)
    - 1888-1890 (Box 11)
    - 1893-1896 (Box 11)
    - 1910 (Box 11)
  - Order books 1872-1907 dates vary, 21 volumes (Box 12)
  - Order books 1872-1907 dates vary, 14 volumes (Box 13)
  - Bill book 1867-1877 (Box 13)
  - Daybooks 1871-1896 dates vary, 8 volumes (Box 14)
  - Daybook December 1899-February 1902 (Volume 1)
  - Weaving room books 1886-1897, 13 volumes (Box 15)
  - Weavers monthly accounts, 3 volumes
    - 1871-1872 (Box 15)
    - 1880 (Box 15)
    - 1883-1885 (Box 15)
  - Cash books 1869-1895 dates vary, 9 volumes (Box 16)
  - Sales and shipping record (Box 16)
  - Bank books 1879-1882, 1901-1903, 3 volumes (Box 16)
  - Inventory books 1868-1899 dates vary, 5 volumes (Box 16)
  - Ledgers 1871-1872, 1901-1902, 3 volumes (Box 17)
  - Index to ledgers (Box 17)
  - Wool room books 1888-1905 dates vary, 7 volumes (Box 17)
  - Stock books 1892-1901 dates vary, 3 volumes (Box 18)
  - Statement books, 2 volumes
    - 1884-1885 (Box 18)
    - 1903-1906 (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous journals, ledgers, and account books 1874-1907 dates vary, 6 volumes (Box 18)
  - Shipping books 1872-1902 dates vary, 10 volumes (Box 19)
  - Charging books 1892-1902, 7 volumes (Box 19)
  - Statements of payrolls in weaving and spinning rooms 1874, 1 folders (Box 19)